<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Models | Ammara Talib</title>
    <link>/tag/models/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/models/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Models</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Models</title>
      <link>/tag/models/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving forecasts of crop water demand with direct ET measurements over irrigated fields</title>
      <link>/conferences/improving-forecasts-of-crop-water-demand-wpvgafeb2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/conferences/improving-forecasts-of-crop-water-demand-wpvgafeb2019/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Conference: &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;UW Extension &amp;amp; Wisconsin Potato &amp;amp; Vegetable Growers Association (WPVGA) Grower Conference 2020&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pines are wetter on the surface. But later the difference between pine and potatoes soil moisture decreases. Pines have more transpiration and less soil evaporation. Deeper in the ground (around 18 inches depth) potatoes have more soil moisture. Water use by different crop types in Midwest (2017,2018) was compared under different soil types. Even same crop type can lead to different water used based on soil condition. Cumulatively corn water loss in Illinois (IL) was about four inches higher than WI potatoes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What have we learned from continuous crop and forest evapotranspiration observations in the Central Sands?</title>
      <link>/conferences/what-have-we-learned-wpvgafeb2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/conferences/what-have-we-learned-wpvgafeb2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Conference: &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;UW Extension &amp;amp; Wisconsin Potato &amp;amp; Vegetable Growers Association (WPVGA) Grower Conference 2019&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ways to measure ET:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meteorological approximations: Thornthwaite, Priestly-Taylor, Penman-Montieth – Strong assumptions on surface properties, ET driven by radiation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Residual: Measure precipitation, soil moisture, runoff, back out ET – Subject to high uncertainty Lysimeters: Labor-intensive, small-area estimate&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remote sensing:  Assumptions on links between electromagnetic radiation and ET, satellites don’t work with clouds&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Process models: Captures all aspects but requires extensive, hard to measure parameters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eddy covariance: Direct method, whole field, expensive and expertise required&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Machine “Learning”: Site-specific, hard to extrapolate or interpret, but powerful for forecasting&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
