<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Drought | Ammara Talib</title>
    <link>/tag/drought/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/drought/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Drought</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Drought</title>
      <link>/tag/drought/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evaluation of prediction and forecasting models for evapotranspiration of agricultural lands in the Midwest US</title>
      <link>/publication/evaluation-of-forecasting-models-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/evaluation-of-forecasting-models-2021/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning data-driven network to estimate and forecast evapotranspiration (ET)</title>
      <link>/research/rnn_et/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/research/rnn_et/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The potentials of random forest (RF) and long short-term memory (LSTM) neural networks to estimate and forecast daily ET for corn, soybeans, and potatoes in diverse agricultural farms was evaluated in this research. The proposed modeling architecture provides a field-scale, locally calibrated tool for accurate prediction and short-term forecasting of daily ET in areas lacking in situ ET, metrological, and biophysical data. Furthermore, since there is no clear understanding of minimum required predictors for accurate estimates of ET, our models with different sets of predictors can help to understand the need for essential or minimum drivers for different crop fields on various soil textures in areas with scarce data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goals of this research include, how well can empirical ML models predict and forecast ET 3 days in advance in irrigated and rain-fed agricultural lands across the Midwest US? And What are important drivers for predicting and forecasting ET 3 days in advance in irrigated and non-irrigated areas?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Picture1&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research/rnn_et/picture1_hu6a031b2fd2c8ab9da733dfc27eba5283_473989_e0e1ae2a7ab58101140346428eb77009.webp 400w,
               /research/rnn_et/picture1_hu6a031b2fd2c8ab9da733dfc27eba5283_473989_21bae816ccd15bbef3b94893a528a1c3.webp 760w,
               /research/rnn_et/picture1_hu6a031b2fd2c8ab9da733dfc27eba5283_473989_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research/rnn_et/picture1_hu6a031b2fd2c8ab9da733dfc27eba5283_473989_e0e1ae2a7ab58101140346428eb77009.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;659&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prediction and forecasting models for ET based on RF and LSTM framework with 5, 11, and 16 predictors was proposed. For all model experiments, simulations were based on daily time step from 2003-2019. The selection of sixteen model input predictors for RF_16 and LSTM_16 model was due to their influence on ET and their availability for agricultural sites. After calibration and validation, empirical models of RF and LSTM were benchmarked against output from process-based model ET from the North American Land Data Assimilation System (NLDAS) version 2 LSM model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The performance of the two ET prediction algorithms for the test data, which demonstrated the ability of the calibrated models to generalize to unseen ET observations (test data) from eddy covariance flux towers across multiple crop types. The evaluation statistics indicated that there is a good agreement between the predicted and observed ET values across corn, soybeans, and potatoes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Picture2&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research/rnn_et/Picture2_huc94ea1dc897fd1ba71798d8eee8ed391_405074_d1d4a40e5230b2fae3415c23c92b64c4.webp 400w,
               /research/rnn_et/Picture2_huc94ea1dc897fd1ba71798d8eee8ed391_405074_e4c45f10ea29383bf82fc160b646d819.webp 760w,
               /research/rnn_et/Picture2_huc94ea1dc897fd1ba71798d8eee8ed391_405074_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research/rnn_et/Picture2_huc94ea1dc897fd1ba71798d8eee8ed391_405074_d1d4a40e5230b2fae3415c23c92b64c4.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;299&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our analysis for RF model showed that VP and crop coefficients were the most important predictors for irrigated crops, while short wave radiation and enhanced vegetation index were key predictors for non-irrigated crops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Picture3&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research/rnn_et/Picture3_hu9a1ad4484dc4df946705862b2dda2a55_497874_0237e58c292ab3a5fdb194ff3ca9901f.webp 400w,
               /research/rnn_et/Picture3_hu9a1ad4484dc4df946705862b2dda2a55_497874_a7ab3574973e935283c3c242b31de22a.webp 760w,
               /research/rnn_et/Picture3_hu9a1ad4484dc4df946705862b2dda2a55_497874_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research/rnn_et/Picture3_hu9a1ad4484dc4df946705862b2dda2a55_497874_0237e58c292ab3a5fdb194ff3ca9901f.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;439&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A multistep forecast model that can forecast ET three days ahead of time using RF and LSTM models was developed. Finally, the importance of model predictors was calculated for both prediction and forecast model versions of RF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022169421006260&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;research paper&lt;/a&gt; detailing the findings of this research has been accepted in the Journal of Hydrology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Groundwater-Surface water interaction in agricultural watershed that encompasses dense network of High Capacity wells</title>
      <link>/conferences/groundwater-surface-water-interaction-in-dense-network-of-high-capacity-wells-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/conferences/groundwater-surface-water-interaction-in-dense-network-of-high-capacity-wells-2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Conference: &amp;lsquo;&lt;em&gt;American Geophysical Union, Fall Meeting 2017&lt;/em&gt; H34D-06&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract: The Central Sands region of Wisconsin is characterized by productive trout streams, lakes, farmland and forest. However,stream channelization, past wetland drainage, and ground water withdrawals have disrupted the hydrology of this CentralSands region. Climatically driven conditions in last decade (2000-2008) alone are unable to account for the severelydepressed water levels. Increased interception and evapotranspiration from afforested areas in central sand Wisconsinmay also be culprit for reduced water recharge. Hence, there is need to study the cumulative effects of changingprecipitation patterns, groundwater withdrawals, and forest evapotranspiration to improve projections of the future of lakelevels and water availability in this region.Here, the SWAT-MODFLOW coupled model approach was applied at large spatio-temporal scale. The coupled model fullyintegrates a watershed model (SWAT) with a groundwater flow model (MODFLOW). Surface water and ground water flowswere simulated integratively at daily time step to estimate the groundwater discharge to the stream network in CentralSands that encompasses high capacity wells. The model was calibrated (2010-2013) and validated (2014-2017) based onstreamflow, groundwater extraction, and water table elevation. As the long-term trends in some of the primary drivers is presently ambiguous in Central Sands under future climate, as isthe case for total precipitation or timing of precipitation, we relied on a sensitivity student to quantitatively access howprimary and secondary drivers may influence future net groundwater recharge. We demonstrate how such an approachcould then be coupled with decision-making models to evaluate the effectiveness of groundwater withdrawal policiesunder a changing climate.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
