<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Researches | Ammara Talib</title>
    <link>/research/</link>
      <atom:link href="/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Researches</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Researches</title>
      <link>/research/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multidecadal evapotranspiration measurements in a temperate forest demonstrate a sustained impact of warmer winters and a transient effect of chronic biotic disturbance</title>
      <link>/research/harvard_forest/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/research/harvard_forest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Over the past few decades, HWA infestation has significantly affected eastern hemlock (Tsuga canadensis) in the eastern U.S., and winters are expected to continue to warm in the future. Direct ET measurements are particularly essential for managing forests as pressures on high-quality surface water supply increase. 
Our study investigates how forest disturbances, climate change, and ET interact to influence the water cycle in the eastern U.S., where surface water regeneration plays a critical role in local water supply systems. 
&lt;p&gt;We hypothesized that the biotic stress and mortality by HWA at the eastern hemlock site would cause an initial decrease in ET followed by an increase as deciduous species replaced hemlock. We also expected to find larger shifts in ET in the non-growing season due to the stress and mortality of the evergreen hemlock trees,
coupled with increasingly warmer winter conditions that allow higher year-round transpiration. At both sites, we hypothesized that the meteorological drivers associated with PET would increase year-round due to higher temperatures and vapor pressure deficit with climate change.
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;picture1&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research/harvard_forest/picture1_hue53c370028bdbfbf4bc6ddb1b70ab024_508322_b4b3e262d55bed63a1158a3b5c8152d6.webp 400w,
               /research/harvard_forest/picture1_hue53c370028bdbfbf4bc6ddb1b70ab024_508322_9e3794e20c1f5e426007998575915846.webp 760w,
               /research/harvard_forest/picture1_hue53c370028bdbfbf4bc6ddb1b70ab024_508322_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research/harvard_forest/picture1_hue53c370028bdbfbf4bc6ddb1b70ab024_508322_b4b3e262d55bed63a1158a3b5c8152d6.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;326&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure demonstrates that both EMS and HEM tower shows a decline in ET in the initial time period. For example, ET has declined significantly (p=1.7^10-2) from 587.2 to 374.2 during 2003-2008 with a negative slope of -9.2 and percent change of 31.5%. HEM tower also showed a significant decline (p=2.9^10-1) in ET from 565.7 to 278.9 mm with a steep slope of -26 and percent change of 60.6%.
After an initial decline in ET at both sites, an increase in ET was observed for the later period of time series. For example, at EMS site, ET was slightly increased (p=6.9*10-1) from 374.2 to 464.5 mm with a slope of 4.1 and percent change of 12%. Similarly HEM site ET also increased from 278.9-424 with a slope of 3.3 and a change of 12%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;picture12&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research/harvard_forest/Picture12_hu675047944353f0e6d6dfa5400a0abf13_2318369_775bafb734d20f7e948ba91a4c6ee848.webp 400w,
               /research/harvard_forest/Picture12_hu675047944353f0e6d6dfa5400a0abf13_2318369_1f0024306a5355ea0f92a15170de6aca.webp 760w,
               /research/harvard_forest/Picture12_hu675047944353f0e6d6dfa5400a0abf13_2318369_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research/harvard_forest/Picture12_hu675047944353f0e6d6dfa5400a0abf13_2318369_775bafb734d20f7e948ba91a4c6ee848.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;312&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The figure shows a significant decrease at a rate of -0.004 mol m-2 s-1 year-1 (38.6%) over this time period (Kendall τ = -0.34, p = 0.007). Time series trends for growing season gs paralleled those of the annual gs with a significant decrease at a rate of -0.006 mol m-2 per year (Kendall τ = -0.40, p = 0.002). At the EMS site the non-growing season gs did not have a significant trend through time.
A t-test found that the mean annual gs of 0.32 mol m-2 s-1 with a range of 0.22–0.42 mol m-2 s-1 (SD=0.05) for 2005-2023 was significantly lower than that of EMS (t-test, p = 2.24^10-16).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;picture13&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research/harvard_forest/Picture13_hu5b057f8ce8f51cd65673db08523adf58_227412_bb1c052a2a21bb9a207f31566d518b9c.webp 400w,
               /research/harvard_forest/Picture13_hu5b057f8ce8f51cd65673db08523adf58_227412_a4da37b8b4ae0749c0ee4bff8e6418fc.webp 760w,
               /research/harvard_forest/Picture13_hu5b057f8ce8f51cd65673db08523adf58_227412_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research/harvard_forest/Picture13_hu5b057f8ce8f51cd65673db08523adf58_227412_bb1c052a2a21bb9a207f31566d518b9c.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;625&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the EMS site, NETRAD was identified as the most influential meteorological factor affecting ET, followed by month, GPP, VPD, and PAR. In contrast, at the HEM site, GPP was the most significant factor influencing ET, followed by NETRAD, NEE, VPD, and Tair.
The correlation between GPP and ET is stronger at the HEM site compared to the EMS site. Conversely, the importance of NETRAD is greater at the EMS site than at the HEM site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://agu.confex.com/agu/hydrology24/meetingapp.cgi/Person/1494288&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt; detailing the findings of this research was delivered in Water Science Conference (WaterSciCon24).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial and temporal Characterization of Forecasting GW Anomalies in Wisconsin Central Sands (WCS)</title>
      <link>/research/gw_anamoly/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/research/gw_anamoly/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
Wisconsin is humid, though GW shortages have been reported in several regions, including the Wisconsin Central Sands (WCS). The shortage of GW in the WCS is caused by many factors, including climate variability, fast expansion of irrigation, increasing high-capacity wells, and increasing population. For sustainable 
water resource management, there is an urgent need to develop a computationally-efficient and easy-to-update  framework with the capability of efficient incorporation of recently developed and regularly updated environmental datasets (e.g., remote sensing maps of evapotranspiration and soil 
moisture).
&lt;p&gt;The research questions for this project include: Using computationally efficient ML models, can easy-to-obtain remote sensing derived environmental datasets be combined to accurately predict GW dynamics across the WCS? How does GW anomaly vary in space and across the WCS? How pumping and crop type change can influence this anomaly forecasting?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Static and dynamic variables were used to build LSTM model for
prediction of GW depth at the 26 well locations in the WCS region monthly from 1958 to 2020.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;picture1&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research/gw_anamoly/picture1_hu15ea8c051bfdff3af30c6498b8ef4365_755931_39ea74abc4f81469445e2067a2797be0.webp 400w,
               /research/gw_anamoly/picture1_hu15ea8c051bfdff3af30c6498b8ef4365_755931_c06e1ffd7b787d5c0b5f1352d1db706d.webp 760w,
               /research/gw_anamoly/picture1_hu15ea8c051bfdff3af30c6498b8ef4365_755931_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research/gw_anamoly/picture1_hu15ea8c051bfdff3af30c6498b8ef4365_755931_39ea74abc4f81469445e2067a2797be0.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;578&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effect of topography-related drivers is more conspicuous than SWE drivers. For example, for four wells, MAE was reduced by greater than 10 %, but for eight wells, MAE increased by greater than 10 %.
Additionally, these three wells with the highest % change in MAE were located on the northeast side of WCS. All drivers, except meteorology-associated drivers, increased MAE for well_4101 when excluded. Well_1701 MAE was also increased when other drivers were excluded except for topography-related drivers. Based on permutation feature importance, PDSI, SW radiation, soil moisture, wind speed, and runoff were among the most important features.
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;picture12&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research/gw_anamoly/Picture12_hu5fbd637db207e95ec6ac933d0cf591a7_341912_c67bace9a948c5e41e20e086e003f165.webp 400w,
               /research/gw_anamoly/Picture12_hu5fbd637db207e95ec6ac933d0cf591a7_341912_3aeeeca09afd1267533dea3dac59301a.webp 760w,
               /research/gw_anamoly/Picture12_hu5fbd637db207e95ec6ac933d0cf591a7_341912_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research/gw_anamoly/Picture12_hu5fbd637db207e95ec6ac933d0cf591a7_341912_c67bace9a948c5e41e20e086e003f165.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;439&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pumping or irrigation demand has a higher relative importance to GW anomalies forecast compared to land use change.
There is a direct connection between pumping and groundwater level change based on simple physics, but initially, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t clear whether irrigation demand would have a more substantial impact on groundwater anomalies than land use change since land use changes determine irrigation demand because of their correlation. Groundwater dynamics are closely related to agricultural irrigation in the WCS.
















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;picture13&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research/gw_anamoly/Picture13_hu107585f971dfa6e36984322aa6f3e586_1071111_2f38a439acbebf0f4156419de96c75bc.webp 400w,
               /research/gw_anamoly/Picture13_hu107585f971dfa6e36984322aa6f3e586_1071111_207b7a7932425f71ba59d3d578de5c8e.webp 760w,
               /research/gw_anamoly/Picture13_hu107585f971dfa6e36984322aa6f3e586_1071111_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research/gw_anamoly/Picture13_hu107585f971dfa6e36984322aa6f3e586_1071111_2f38a439acbebf0f4156419de96c75bc.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;730&#34;
               height=&#34;760&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our observations, negative anomaly means shallow GW, so pumping has greater influence on shallow GW. Hence model can better estimate anomaly for shallower water. Pumping makes GW deeper so the anomaly becomes positive.
I hope to submit my manuscript for this research project by January 2022.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;picture11&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research/gw_anamoly/Picture11_hu37cd4f5a1294f9221c9f661ddc03685d_423300_1023e0cebd198b3058548a91e6c978b3.webp 400w,
               /research/gw_anamoly/Picture11_hu37cd4f5a1294f9221c9f661ddc03685d_423300_05dd78bb9ca77b291b4629734d23ddee.webp 760w,
               /research/gw_anamoly/Picture11_hu37cd4f5a1294f9221c9f661ddc03685d_423300_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research/gw_anamoly/Picture11_hu37cd4f5a1294f9221c9f661ddc03685d_423300_1023e0cebd198b3058548a91e6c978b3.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;364&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agrformet.2024.109967&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;research paper&lt;/a&gt; detailing the findings of this research has been accepted in the Journal of Hydrology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning data-driven network to estimate and forecast evapotranspiration (ET)</title>
      <link>/research/rnn_et/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/research/rnn_et/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify;&#34;&gt;
The potentials of random forest (RF) and long short-term memory (LSTM) neural networks to estimate and forecast daily ET for corn, soybeans, and potatoes in diverse agricultural farms was evaluated in this research. The proposed modeling architecture provides a field-scale, locally calibrated tool for accurate prediction and short-term forecasting of daily ET in areas lacking in situ ET, metrological, and biophysical data. Furthermore, since there is no clear understanding of minimum required predictors for accurate estimates of ET, our models with different sets of predictors can help to understand the need for essential or minimum drivers for different crop fields on various soil textures in areas with scarce data. 
&lt;p&gt;The goals of this research include, how well can empirical ML models predict and forecast ET 3 days in advance in irrigated and rain-fed agricultural lands across the Midwest US? And What are important drivers for predicting and forecasting ET 3 days in advance in irrigated and non-irrigated areas?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Picture1&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research/rnn_et/picture1_hu6a031b2fd2c8ab9da733dfc27eba5283_473989_e0e1ae2a7ab58101140346428eb77009.webp 400w,
               /research/rnn_et/picture1_hu6a031b2fd2c8ab9da733dfc27eba5283_473989_21bae816ccd15bbef3b94893a528a1c3.webp 760w,
               /research/rnn_et/picture1_hu6a031b2fd2c8ab9da733dfc27eba5283_473989_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research/rnn_et/picture1_hu6a031b2fd2c8ab9da733dfc27eba5283_473989_e0e1ae2a7ab58101140346428eb77009.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;659&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prediction and forecasting models for ET based on RF and LSTM framework with 5, 11, and 16 predictors was proposed. For all model experiments, simulations were based on daily time step from 2003-2019. The selection of sixteen model input predictors for RF_16 and LSTM_16 model was due to their influence on ET and their availability for agricultural sites. After calibration and validation, empirical models of RF and LSTM were benchmarked against output from process-based model ET from the North American Land Data Assimilation System (NLDAS) version 2 LSM model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The performance of the two ET prediction algorithms for the test data, which demonstrated the ability of the calibrated models to generalize to unseen ET observations (test data) from eddy covariance flux towers across multiple crop types. The evaluation statistics indicated that there is a good agreement between the predicted and observed ET values across corn, soybeans, and potatoes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Picture2&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research/rnn_et/Picture2_huc94ea1dc897fd1ba71798d8eee8ed391_405074_d1d4a40e5230b2fae3415c23c92b64c4.webp 400w,
               /research/rnn_et/Picture2_huc94ea1dc897fd1ba71798d8eee8ed391_405074_e4c45f10ea29383bf82fc160b646d819.webp 760w,
               /research/rnn_et/Picture2_huc94ea1dc897fd1ba71798d8eee8ed391_405074_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research/rnn_et/Picture2_huc94ea1dc897fd1ba71798d8eee8ed391_405074_d1d4a40e5230b2fae3415c23c92b64c4.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;299&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our analysis for RF model showed that VP and crop coefficients were the most important predictors for irrigated crops, while short wave radiation and enhanced vegetation index were key predictors for non-irrigated crops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Picture3&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research/rnn_et/Picture3_hu9a1ad4484dc4df946705862b2dda2a55_497874_0237e58c292ab3a5fdb194ff3ca9901f.webp 400w,
               /research/rnn_et/Picture3_hu9a1ad4484dc4df946705862b2dda2a55_497874_a7ab3574973e935283c3c242b31de22a.webp 760w,
               /research/rnn_et/Picture3_hu9a1ad4484dc4df946705862b2dda2a55_497874_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research/rnn_et/Picture3_hu9a1ad4484dc4df946705862b2dda2a55_497874_0237e58c292ab3a5fdb194ff3ca9901f.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;439&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A multistep forecast model that can forecast ET three days ahead of time using RF and LSTM models was developed. Finally, the importance of model predictors was calculated for both prediction and forecast model versions of RF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
A [research paper](https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhydrol.2021.126579) detailing the findings of this research has been accepted in the Journal of Hydrology. 
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving parameterization of atmospheric emissivity of a regional model for evapotranspiration estimation</title>
      <link>/research/wisp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/research/wisp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first chapter of my thesis seeks to improve the parameterization of atmospheric emissivity of a regional irrigation scheduling program for evapotranspiration estimation using eddy covariance measurements. The performance of land surface model-based AET, reanalysis, and remote sensing products varies at different spatio-temporal scales. In the Central Sands Regions of Wisconsin, irrigation agriculture plays a fundamental role in supporting regional agricultural production and rural community development. For irrigation scheduling, farmers often rely on the Wisconsin Irrigation and Scheduling Program (WISP) model, developed by soil scientists at UW-Madison and based on satellite data. WISP is a regional model based on the Priestley Taylor approach and provides Potential ET (PET) estimates that can be scaled to ET based on percent canopy cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;picture1&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research/wisp/picture1_huf449459473f3c3a22e0e164a92cef22d_750066_9a0b2a8029f2a789db2d6284525a576e.webp 400w,
               /research/wisp/picture1_huf449459473f3c3a22e0e164a92cef22d_750066_400bae08cc5a0b6368c19aa9e0f9aa2e.webp 760w,
               /research/wisp/picture1_huf449459473f3c3a22e0e164a92cef22d_750066_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research/wisp/picture1_huf449459473f3c3a22e0e164a92cef22d_750066_9a0b2a8029f2a789db2d6284525a576e.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;714&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2018, with support from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://wisconsinpotatoes.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Wisconsin Potato and Vegetable Growers Association&lt;/a&gt; Water Task Force, &lt;a href=&#34;https://dnr.wisconsin.gov/topic/Groundwater/GCC/research.htm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources&lt;/a&gt;, and the UW &lt;a href=&#34;https://ccr.nelson.wisc.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Center for Climatic Research&lt;/a&gt;, our lab installed eddy covariance flux towers on a center-pivot irrigated potato field (US-CS1) from June 2018-May 2019, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tricounty.k12.wi.us/district/schoolforest.cfm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Tri-County School Forest&lt;/a&gt; pine stand Sept 2018-, a 2nd potato field (US-CS3) from June 2019-June 2020, and a 3rd potato field (US-CS4) from June 2020-present. Links to graphs, tables, and publications are at project website [Water use in Wisconsin Potatoes and Pine] (&lt;a href=&#34;https://flux.aos.wisc.edu/potato&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://flux.aos.wisc.edu/potato&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research evaluates sources of bias in the WISP model and develops a correction using eddy covariance (EC) observations. AET observations were made for five years (2018–2022), using EC systems in irrigated potatoes fields in Wisconsin Central Sands (WCS) region. Multi-source ET datasets should be employed in future studies to enhance confidence in remotely sensed ET related water budgets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The source of uncertainty in the model could be due to model inputs of coefficients used in empirical equations. Those coefficients are not regionally calibrated, which could lead to underestimating the energy budget.
Wisconsin is humid, where ET is energy limited, and by correcting the energy budget, we expect to see reduced bias in model ET.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;picture12&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research/wisp/Picture12_huf449459473f3c3a22e0e164a92cef22d_1675916_8c5d8599399daf0e3a5f187cf464a6ee.webp 400w,
               /research/wisp/Picture12_huf449459473f3c3a22e0e164a92cef22d_1675916_6c770f5cb6c26049b142e2860a510922.webp 760w,
               /research/wisp/Picture12_huf449459473f3c3a22e0e164a92cef22d_1675916_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research/wisp/Picture12_huf449459473f3c3a22e0e164a92cef22d_1675916_8c5d8599399daf0e3a5f187cf464a6ee.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;732&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The WISP model
overestimated ET before correction because modeled AET range for the WCS region was 7.17-7.48 mm before correction for July 19th, 2020, but after correction modeled
AET_corr range was 5.59-5.86 mm. Total AET for the entire region for July 19th, 2020, is 569 mm before correction and 444.5 mm after modification, with a difference of 124.5 mm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;picture13&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /research/wisp/Picture13_huf449459473f3c3a22e0e164a92cef22d_901341_534378872235641e950a43da01a9750c.webp 400w,
               /research/wisp/Picture13_huf449459473f3c3a22e0e164a92cef22d_901341_84785041d6cdf0d46fb89e1eafdf2955.webp 760w,
               /research/wisp/Picture13_huf449459473f3c3a22e0e164a92cef22d_901341_1200x1200_fit_q75_h2_lanczos_3.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;/research/wisp/Picture13_huf449459473f3c3a22e0e164a92cef22d_901341_534378872235641e950a43da01a9750c.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;423&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agrformet.2024.109967&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;research paper&lt;/a&gt; detailing the findings of this research has been accepted in the journal of Agricultural and Forest Meteorology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
